Finding Aid for Kelsey Museum of Archaeology papers 1890-1987
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Kelsey Museum of Archaeology papers
1890-1987
Kelsey Museum of Archaeology.
Papers of Francis W. Kelsey, University of Michigan professor of Latin (for whom Museum was named); papers of Museum directors and curators, principally Orma F. Butler, Enoch E. Peterson, Louise A. Shier, John G. Winter; papers of University faculty associated with the Museum or the study and teaching of classical and medieval studies, notably Arthur E.R. Boak, Campbell Bonner, Thomas S. Jerome, and Robert H. McDowell; also records of the Institute of Archaeological Research, and material on 1975-1979 Carthage expedition.
89487 Bimu C450 2
131.5 linear feet in 244 boxes
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The Kelsey Museum of Archaeology papers were transferred to the Bentley Historical Library in 1989 (Donor no. 6687 ). There have been several small subsequent accessions.
The papers are open without restriction.
In the fall of 1928, following the death of Francis Kelsey the year before, John Winter, Campbell Bonner, Arthur Boak and Leroy Watermann, Professors at the University of Michigan, prevailed upon the Director of Museums, Alexander Ruthven, to provide a setting for the archaeological artifacts which had accumulated during Francis Kelsey's tenure as Professor of Latin at the University. Professor Kelsey had maintained a keen interest in collecting artifacts and promoting the archeological expeditions sponsored by the University of Michigan. In 1929 a Museum of Art and Archaeology was established in Newberry Hall: after some renovation, the artifacts were transferred to the museum in the spring of 1929. The name was changed to the Kelsey Museum of Ancient and Mediaeval Archaeology (hereafter called the Kelsey Museum) in 1953. Heretofore, these artifacts had been stored in the old University Library (now the Graduate Library), the basement of Alumni Memorial Hall (now the University Art Museum) and Angell Hall.
In addition, it is probable that the records of Francis Kelsey and those of Thomas Spencer Jerome were transferred to the Museum at the same time. Jerome, an alumnus of the University who died in 1914, left a number of books to the University library, as well as funds which were used to establish the Jerome Lectureships: the lectures are given biannually in Rome and Michigan to further historical research. The Kelsey and Jerome records were found in the Museum attic early in 1980. Since that time both collections have been arranged, stored archivally and finding aids produced.
In 1980, Elizabeth Savage who had been Registrar of the Kelsey Museum and Pam Reister, who was her assistant, discovered many Museum records and photographs on the second floor, in a section now known as the Range Area Room. After the records were searched, some material was discarded, and the remainder disbursed to various parts of the Museum. These records included the files of Orma Butler: first Curator of the Museum from 1928 to 1938; Enoch Peterson: with the museum for a number of years and Director from 1950-1962; Louise Shier (who retired in 1977): originally an aide to Orma Butler, then Curator and finally interim Director in the early 1970's; John Winter: first Director of the Museum from 1929 to 1950; and Campbell Bonner and Henry Sanders: Professors at the University who were close associates of Kelsey and who served on the Museum committee for many years. The records also contained files of the Institute for Archaeological Research (formerly the Near East Research Committee). These second floor records were transferred to the attic of the Museum.
In 1989 the Kelsey Museum papers was transferred to the Bentley Historical Library. The Bentley Historical Library staff provides reference service for the collection. The Kelsey Museum retains title to the collection.
Introduction
The Francis W. Kelsey Museum of Archaeology was founded in 1928 to house, care for, and exhibit the university's growing collection of ancient artifacts acquired through purchase, gift or as the result of archaeological excavations by university faculty.
Francis W. Kelsey, Professor of Latin Language and Literature, 1889-1927, began the university's archaeological apart of his extensive travels and research in the Mediterranean, Near East and North Africa. In 1924 Kelsey organized the first of a series of excavation in Egypt and Iraq under the auspices of the Institute for Archaeological Research with funding provided by Horace Rackham.
Professor Arthur E.R. Boak directed the initial excavations at Karanis, Egypt, which continued through 1935 under the Professor Enoch E. Peterson. Major excavations were also conducted at Dimé and Terenouthis. Kelsey chose Professor David Robinson of Johns Hopkins University to lead the Asia Minor expedition. The Michigan team initially assistance William Ramsey excavation of the site of Roman Antioch at Pisidia. Robinson later received permission form the Turkish authorities to begin excavations at Sizma, near Konia. The core of the Museum's collection derives from these excavations.
After Kelsey's death in 1927 a Museum of Classical Archaeology was established as part of the University Museums, with Professor John G. .Winter of the Department of Latin and Greek as director and Dr. Orma Fitch Butler as curator. In 1940 the museum became a separate reassert unit of the University under the title Museum of Art and Archaeology. as renamed the Museum of Archaeology when the Art Museum was made a separate entity. The Board of Regents recognized Kelsey's pioneering work by renaming the museum the Francis W. Kelsey Museum of Archaeology in 1953.
From its founding the Kelsey Museum has been located in the former Student Christian Association building on State Street.
The Kelsey Museum now houses a collection of nearly 100,000 objects from the civilizations of the Mediterranean. A selection of these artifacts are featured in two permanent galleries: Egypt and the Ancient Near East, and Greece, Etruria, Rome, 5000 BC - AD 900, as well as in a gallery with annual changing exhibitions. The museum also sponsors research, educational programs for children, oversees fieldwork projects, and serves as the home for the Interdepartmental Program in Classical Art and Archaeology.
Museum Directors
1929-1950 John Garrett Winter
1950-1961 Enoch Ernest Peterson
1961-1969 George Forsythe, Jr.
1969-1971 Theodore V. Buttrey
1971-1972 Louise Adele Shier (acting)
1972-1973 Louise Adele Shier
1973-1986 John Pedley
1986-1997 Elaine Gazda
1997-current Sharon C. Herbert
Museum Curators
1928-1938 Orma Fitch Butler
1938-1950 Enoch Ernest Peterson
1950-1973 Louise Adele Shier
1973-current Sharon C. Herbert
1974- current Elaine K. Gazda
1978-current Margaret Cool Root
1988-current Thelma K. Thomas
1993- 1995 John Humphrey
1994-current Robin Meador-Woodruff (Collections Manager since 1988)
1994-current Janet E. Richards
1994-current Terry Wilfong
2001-current Suzanne Davis
2002-current Susan Alcock
2002-current John F. Cherry
Arthur E.R. Boak
Arthur E. R. Boak (as he was known), was born in Halifax, Nova Scotia on April 29, 1888. He received a Master of Arts degree from Queens University, Kingston, Ontario in 1907, and then attended Harvard where he received a second Master's degree in 1911 and the Ph.D. in 1914. He joined the University of Michigan in 1914 and taught history for the next forty-four years.
Boak was considered to be one of the most prominent of American and world scholars in ancient history. He was a Henry Russell Lecturer in 1949-1950 and was awarded the Jerome Lectureship in 1951-1952. Earlier, he had served on the staff of the University of Michigan expedition to Karanis during the 1924-1925 season and again in 1931-1932.
Boak was active in many societies: he was a fellow of the International Institute of Arts and Letters, a member of the American Historical Association, American Philological Association, The Society for the Promotion of Roman Studies, Association Internationale de Papyrologues, the U.S. Naval Institute; the Archaeological Institute of America, the Bavarian Academy of Arts, Science and Letters, the Medieval Academy of America, the Research Club of the University of Michigan; he served on the Board of Editors and Council of the American Historical Association and the Council of Mediaeval Academy.
Boak was the author or co-author of eleven books, including The History of Our World (1954) and A History of Rome to 565 A.D. (1955). When he died on December 16, 1962, Boak was eulogized for his devotion to his students and his contributions to the field of history.
Campbell Bonner
Campbell Bonner was born in Nashville, Tennessee on January 30, 1876. He received the A.B. degree at Vanderbilt University in 1896, and the A.M. (in 1898) and Ph.D. (in 1900) from Harvard. Bonner studied at the University of Berlin during the winter of 1900-01, and traveled extensively in Greece and Italy in 1901. He taught at Peabody College for Teachers at the University of Nashville from 1906 to 1907 and then came to the University of Michigan where he taught for the next forty years, earning the title of Professor Emeritus upon his retirement in 1947.
Bonner's specialty was deciphering inscriptions on gnostic gems and stones; he was also noted for his translations of ancient Greek writings. He served as president of several societies: the American Philological Association (1933), the Classical Association of the Middle West and South (1918-1919) and the Michigan Academy of Science, Arts and Letters (1923-1924). Bonner was a member of the Archaeological Institute of America, the American Philosophical Society and Phi Beta Kappa; a fellow of the American Academy of Science, a corresponding fellow of the British Academy, and served on the Managing Committee of the American School of Classical Studies in Athens.
His published writings include A Papyrus Codex of the Shepherd of Hermas (1933), The Last Chapters of Enoch in Greek (1937), The Homily of the Passion by Melito Bishop of Sardis (1940) and Studies in the Magical Amulets (1949).
Campbell Bonner died in 1954.
Institute of Archaeological Research
A group of records designated by the office of origin as the "Institute of Archaeological Research" (hereafter known as the I.A.R.), are actually the files of one continuous Committee. The responsibilities and name of the Committee evolved over the years; however, the original purpose of the Committee remained as when it was first convened, namely interest in Near East research. Although records of the Advisory Committee on Near East Research and the Near East Research Committee were filed under "N," these records actually preceded "Institute" records. The I.A.R. later became the Committee on Research. Following is a brief summary of the formation of this committee.
Shortly after World War I, Francis Kelsey took a leave of absence from the University and made several trips to Europe to purchase additional artifacts for the University of Michigan collections. Costs were underwritten by friends of the University. In 1923, Horace Rackham of Detroit gave $100,000, payable over two years to support research in the humanities. This donation made possible the first of many expeditions to Egypt, notably to Karanis in the Fayoum district. An informal group known as the Advisory Committee on Near East Research was established in January 1924 to oversee this fund and formulate general policies regarding the expedition. President Marion Burton, Deans John Effinger and Alfred Lloyd, Professors Arthur Boak, Campbell Bonner, John Winter, Henry Sanders and Frank Robbins and Librarian William Bishop served as advisors.
The first expedition was divided into sections and began work at Karanis, Antioch in Pisidia and Sizma in 1924. Work at Karanis continued until 1935. A small expedition was sent to Carthage in 1925 but work terminated there after one season. In the mid-thirties, digging resumed at Dimé which was surveyed about the time that work began at Karanis. In 1935, the last excavations took place at Terenouthis, now called Kom Abou Bilou.
After Kelsey's death in 1927, the Board of Regents gave the Advisory Committee specific authority to direct all activities connected with the Karanis expedition and changed its title to the Committee on Near East Research. However, several years later further changes became necessary. On April 30, 1931, the Board of Regents mandated that the designation Institute of Archaeological Research was to replace the Committee title. There were several reasons: an Institute would suggest more permanence and prestige than a "Committee," an Institute would command more respect when seeking funds and grants, and the new title and structure would facilitate the coordination and control of various projects. The charter of the I.A.R. was to promote archaeological excavations, carry out the study and publication of archaeological material and foster other studies associated with archaeological work.
Institute officers consisted of a Director, who supervised the affairs and policies of the Institute, and an Executive Secretary, who managed the business affairs and took care of all official correspondence and publicity. These two, together with one other member chosen from the Institute, constituted the Executive Committee. They were appointed annually by the Board of Regents on nomination by the Institute and held office until successors were appointed. In fact, most members served on this committee for a number of years. New people were appointed if a member asked to be excused or if a vacancy arose due to the death of a member.
In addition to the Egyptian expeditions sponsored by the University from 1924 to 1937, the I.A.R. in conjunction with the Toledo Museum of Art, in 1928 financed an expedition begun by Professor Leroy Waterman at Tel Umar in Iraq. Support continued from 1929 to 1930, and from 1930 to 1931, support was carried on with the additional help of the Cleveland Museum of Art. Work ceased for several years during the economic depression, then resumed from 1936 to 1937 under Clark Hopkins.
Aside from funds allocated for the expeditions, an appropriation of $250,000 spread over five years was given by the General Education Board to assist in work related to the expeditions and performed in Ann Arbor. Sixteen volumes were published by the University in the Humanistic Series; these included reports on the excavations and monographs devoted to papyri, ostraca, Egyptian textiles and Parthian pottery.
In the fall of 1938 the by-laws of the University were being revised by Provost E. B. Stetson; he suggested that the group consider a new name, as the name I.A.R. "did not appear to express with entire accuracy the Institute's purposes." In 1941 the Regents accepted the following changes. The President would appoint a Committee on Research, to be attached to the Museum of Art and Archaeology, whose focus would be Mediterranean lands and the Near East. Its duties were specifically limited to "the acquisition of archaeological materials, including papyrological and paleographical collections from these regions, and to the formulation of plans for their study and publication." The Committee was also empowered to establish regulations for the use and study of collections by scholars who were not connected with the University. The Committee was to promote and be responsible for the general direction and oversight of archaeological excavations, including preparing budgets and nominating personnel to serve in the field.
After the Regents approved these recommendations, the obligations and membership of the Institute were transferred to the new Committee on Research. Among others, these members included the President, Dean of the College of Literature, Science and the Arts, and Dean of the Graduate School; the Director of the Museum of Art and Archaeology served as an ex officio member of the Committee. The officers and members of the Executive Committee on Research were the same as those of the Institute and they continued to carry out essentially the same duties as previously. This Committee functioned until 1949.
Thomas Spencer Jerome
Thomas Spencer Jerome, benefactor of the Jerome Lectureships given bi-annually at the University of Michigan and the American Academy in Rome, was born on January 24, 1864 in Saginaw, Michigan. Son of ex-Governor David Jerome and Lucey Amelia Peck Jerome, he attended the University of Michigan, graduating in 1884 with the A.B. degree, He spent the next year studying law, then went on to take a Master of Arts degree at Harvard in 1887.
He practiced law in Detroit for the next decade; however, he looked forward to early retirement so that he could devote himself to the study of ancient history. In 1898 Jerome was appointed by the Secretary of War as Counsel to the Transportation Division headed by Colonel Frank J. Hecker in Cuba, during the Spanish-American War. According to Col. Hecker, "...Jerome rendered most valuable service to the government, and was of great assistance to me personally in the difficult duties I had...." He cited Jerome's conversance with the Spanish language, his legal training and quick mind as great assets in expediting arrangements with the Cuban railroad officials to transport the Army of Occupation. Jerome also negotiated the building of track from the Bay of Havanna to the Cuban railway system, thereby avoiding use of the warehouses and docks inhabited by the Spanish soldiers, an area which was known to be infested with yellow fever.
Jerome went on to serve as Consular Agent in Sorrento, Italy (1900-1901), then took up permanent duties as Consular Agent in Capri, Italy. There he immersed himself in the study of ancient civilizations. It is interesting to note that in his reply to the Michigan Alumni questionnaire in 1901, he lists under occupation, "Retired, resident in Capri, Italy," but in 1910, under the same heading he answered, "Historical Student." Despite the pain brought on by his recurrent gastric illness, Jerome spent the years in Capri reading, studying and writing about history. He amassed a great quantity of notes which were carefully filed. From these he wrote monographs, articles, gave a series of lectures at the American Academy in Rome (1911), in Capri (1912) and presented a paper in London before the International Congress of Historical Studies (1913). Jerome published a book in 1914 Roman Memories in the Landscape Seen From Capri. He was editing and re-writing a major portion of his manuscripts for-publication of a larger work dealing with the causes of the fall of the Roman Empire at the time of his death on April 12, 1914 from a gastric hemmorage. He was buried in a nearby cemetery on his beloved island of Capri.
Francis Willey Kelsey
Francis Willey Kelsey, for whom the Archaeological Museum at the University of Michigan is named, was born in Ogden, New York, May 23, 1858. After graduating from the University of Rochester in 1880, he went on to study in Europe (1883-1885). Kelsey received the Ph.D. degree from. the University of Rochester in 1886 and became a professor of Latin at Lake Forest College (1882-1889): in 1889 he took the chair previously held by Professor Henry Frieze at the University of Michigan, as Professor of the Latin Language and Literature. He was awarded an honorary LL.D. degree from the University of Rochester in 1910.
Kelsey's interests were many fold, his efforts tireless, and his mind always eager to tackle a new subject or devise new methods of attacking old problems. As an educator, Kelsey was loved by pupils and esteemed by his colleagues: pupils and professionals alike increasingly sought his advice and counsel on a myriad of matters. Kelsey was respected as a learned, accurate writer and editor. He was compared to University of Michigan President James Angell in his use of "calm, serene, high-minded, simple English." His accomplishments as a writer and editor kept him at the forefront of classical education. Always a champion of a sound classical education, he edited Greek and Latin in American Education (1911). His editions of Caesar's Gallic War, Cicero's Cato Maior de Senectute, Laelius de Amicitia, Cicero's Orations, Ovid, Lucretius and Xenophon's Anabasis (with Professor Zenos) are considered first class resource books even today, some 85 years after publication. He translated August Mau's Pompeii, Its Life and Art and was at work on a huge detailed /study of Pompeii When he died in 1927. The many articles contributed to scholarly and popular journals reflected his interests in education, the classics, religion and archaeology. From 1890 until his death he was editor (with Professor Percy Gardner) of the Handbooks of Archaeology and Antiquities published by Macmillan: he edited with Professor Henry Sanders more than fifteen volumes in the Humanistic Series published by the University of Michigan.
Kelsey was active in many professional societies also reflecting his broad interests: these included the Schoolmaster's Club, the American Association for the Advancement of Science, the American Historical Association, the Classical Association of the Middle West and South, the Classical Association of Great Britain, and the Deutsches Archeologisches Institut. He was a corresponding member of the Academie des Inscriptions et Belle- Lettres of Paris. Kelsey served as President of the American Philological Association, 1906-1907, and President of the Archaeological Institute of America, 1907-1912. During his "five year tenure, the Institute launched new ventures, such as sponsorship of an expedition to Cyrene in 1910-1911. Kelsey was also instrumental in shaping policy for the schools of archaeology both here and abroad: he helped establish new schools in addition to maintaining a continued active interest in the management of those already in operation.
Kelsey's interest in archaeology prompted him to organize five expeditions to the Near East for the University of Michigan from 1919 until his death. In 1920 Kelsey supervised a detailed survey of the battlefields of Julius Caesar in France and Belgium; he then went to Turkey where he explored Roman ruins and studied ancient manuscripts found there. Excavations at Pisidion-Antioch and Sizma in 1924, revealed ruins of a church where Paul may have preached, and fine examples of Roman antiquities. He directed a 1925 expedition to Carthage, and excavations in Karanis revealed a typical Egyptian town in the Graeco-Roman period.
Kelsey made numerous and lasting contributions to the University of Michigan. Paul Bulkley, Assistant Secretary at the University, once suggested to Kelsey that a book be written titled, "The Gifts [to the University of Michigan] Which Have Come Through Professor Kelsey." Kelsey had a deep love for music and for many years he served as President of the Musical Society. Through his personal efforts, the Choral Union Series flourished and grew by attracting such performers as Caruso and Paderewski to Ann Arbor. Kelsey was a prime force in securing funds to build Hill Auditorium. President Harvey Hutchins called him "visionary" when Kelsey suggested locating the auditorium on the site it occupies today. He was instrumental in efforts to secure the great organ which was exhibited at the Chicago World's Fair, and brought it to Michigan as a memorial to Henry Frieze; the cost was underwritten by the many people personally contacted by Kelsey. However, his dream of building a large, moveable stage so that grand opera could be performed at the Hill auditorium was not to be. Kelsey urged that Albert Stanley's work on Greek Themes in Modern Musical Settings be published in the Humanistic Series:-and secured the Stearns collection of rare musical instruments for the University.